Okay, in this lesson we're going to be tackling a key skill with working with union
types and that is how to do type guards and narrowing.
So when a variable could be multiple types, types groups need some help, figure out which
one it is and that's where type guards come in for us.
They let us safely narrow down the type and unlock the right behaviour that we want.
Not exactly is type and narrowing, but type narrowing means reducing a union type to a more
specific type based on runtime checks that we write.
So TypeScript carefully watches our logic and then narrows the type automatically and
this sounds pretty cool.
So I've always let's do an example of this.
So let's have a function and call it perhaps print ID and this is going to take a union
type where we have an ID of string or it's a number.
Now we can do is we can use the type of function here, so we can use the type of keyword
here, the check the type, so if type of, so t, t, y, p, e, booby, type of ID is a string,
then we can do whatever we want to do, we can just do console log, let's say, console
log ID to uppercase, because we know it's a string, otherwise we can do whatever we want
to do here, so we can do say console log ID to fixed and notice the intelligence and
you here that we're coming to this code and automatically give us our two fixed function
here and we can set that to whatever, so the type of acts as the R type guard is basically
a runtime check that helps TypeScript narrow the type.
So we've learnt about type of and how we can use it and there is also another one called
instance of, so instance of like this, instance of, so let's do another function just
so you can see how that works, so function this time we're going to call it handle
date, going to receive in an input type string which is also a date and now we can check
the input instance of is an instance of a date, so we're even checking the actual do type
of, we're actually checking to see whether we actually have a date being passed in and
then if we have we can do what we want to do here, console log, let's say input and do
say two ISO string, blah blah blah, otherwise going to come into here and we know that
we have a string rather than a date, so you can do console log and then say new date, take
our inputs and say two ISO string, so now we're converting that string into a date, so
instance of is useful for doing like class based checks, like perhaps checking for data
or checking for error or any customer classes rather than using type of which is more for
checking primitive types, now if we have a string, we have a boolean or a number for example,
we can also have a third way of doing a type guard that sees the keyword in, so if we're
checking that something is in an actual object we can do that, so let's have a type of dog
and the dog as a method called bark and do user keyword void, so basically it means we're
not defining the implementation for this function and it just returns nothing, then we have
a type of cat, cat says meow, dysfunction, also returns nothing, let's have a function make
it sound and we're going to pass an animal in an in more, so parameter and the animal is
over a dog or it's a cat, so far so good, and now we can check whether the method, there's
a method called bark, there's exists on that animal that passing in, that's why we use
in, so if there's a method called bark, we put adding quotes in animal, then we can do
call animal bark, otherwise we're going to call animal dot meow, again you can see in
silence coming here and already working through the code and giving us the actual function that
we can call, so the in operator allows us to check for property existence, which is really
good for if you have discriminated unions or any situation where you want to have two different
types and you can't necessarily guarantee the functions exists on either those two objects,
let's now take this one step further and work in a more complex example, so let's have
a type of fish and we're going to have swim, this is also going to return void, another
type of bird, this is fly, okay now we're going to have a function called is fish and we're
going to buy a pet, a pet is a type fish or is a type bird and now if it's a fish,
we're going to force it to return a colon and going to force it by doing is fish and then
if it is fish, so we're checking to see if it's fish, then we can now do our return and
cast the pet as a fish, the pet as fish and then we can call a method swim and just if
it's called a method swim, if it's not undefined, we can also then have a function called
move and the move and to supply the pet which is either a fish or a bird and then if we call
our function is fish and if it is fish, where we supply the pet, then we call our method
swim because we've narrowed the actual pet as a fish by calling our function here, otherwise
we can then do pet fly, okay, so this person is pretty powerful as you can see for whenever
we have a complex union and when we're working external data, obviously we're talking
about the fishes and birds here, but you can see substitute these for more appropriate
types in your particular situation and now let's work with an even more appropriate example
and let's say you wanted to get an area of perhaps a circle or a square, so let's create
a type of shape and we can this time we're going to use a discriminated union which
you've learned right and towards the start where we put a pipe here, we're going to say
our shape as a kind and the kind is over going to be circle or square, so if it's a circle
and then we're going to have a radius, radius has a number or we're going to have another
kind and this is going to be square which we have a number of sides and that is a number,
we can have a function called get area where we supply our shape, now this is type of shape
and this is going to return a number where there's a radius or a side, now if the kind
of our shape is circle then we're going to return our little bit of maths here, so you can
do math pi times shape radius times two, all the times two, all the square up two, otherwise
if we have a square, we can simply do return shape, count the number of sides and turn
the square of those, so type guards let us safely work with union types by narrowing
them down at run time and we've learned trying to use type of, we've also learned about
instance of and in as well as doing a custom guard here and also a custom guard in order
to make sure that we do the right behaviour.